<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>WWF - News about the conservation of endangered species</title>
  		<description>News, publications and job feeds from WWF - the global conservation organization </description>
		<managingEditor>WWF - no_reply@panda.org</managingEditor>
<image>
<title>WWF News</title>
<width>70</width>

<height>93</height>
<link>http://www.panda.org/news</link>
<url>http://www.panda.org/img/rsschannellogo.jpg</url>
</image>
		<link>http://www.panda.org</link>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>WWF hails Interpol efforts to curb illegal wildlife trade</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=190205</link>

				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=190205&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/web_107234_311602.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;98&quot; alt=&quot;Demand for tiger body parts used in traditional Chinese medicine and habitat fragmentation from unsustainable regional infrastructure development have driven the decline of the region’s Indochinese tiger population.  &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;Edward Parker/WWF-Canon&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;WWF hails the efforts of a recent worldwide Interpol operation to curb the illegal trade in traditional medicines containing endangered animal and plant species. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
&apos;Given that this crosses many borders, co-ordinating effective efforts to tackle the illegal trade in wildlife is not easy,&apos; said WWF-UK&apos;s wildilfe trade advisor, Heather Sohl. &quot;It&apos;s great to see 18 countries all working simultaneously to investigate and curtail the trade in traditional medicines containing threatened species.  This can be a blueprint for future action on other areas of illicit wildlife trade too.&apos;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The bust comes as WWF is preparing to call on countries which are members of the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES) to improve law enforcement, using intelligence-led, coordinated and cross-border approaches, to stop the illegal wildlife trade, when they meet in Doha, Qatar from 13 to 25 March. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&apos;Such measures will help protect some of our most valued and yet threatened species such as tigers, rhino and elephants,&apos; Sohl said. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Interpol conducted a month-long investigation into&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt; the illegal trade in traditional medicines  containing protected  wildlife products across 18 countries, according to its website. The investigationresulted in a series of  arrests worldwide and the seizure  of thousands of illegal medicines  worth more than EUR 10 million.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
For more details about the operation, which were released today, see http://www.interpol.int/Public/ICPO/PressReleases/PR2010/PR014.asp&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2010-03-05</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>WWF welcomes US backing for Atlantic bluefin tuna international trade ban</title>

				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=190021</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=190021&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/bluefin_1_164761.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;97&quot; alt=&quot;Bluefin tuna stock in the Mediterranean is threatened by overfishing and illegal fishing. &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;Brian Skerry / National Geographic Image Collection&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Washington, D.C.&lt;/strong&gt; – WWF welcomes today’s announcement that the United States government will vote for a ban on international commercial trade in Atlantic bluefin tuna during a meeting of the largest wildlife trade convention later this month.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
Joining a growing list of supporting countries, the U.S. announced today that it would vote to list the Atlantic bluefin tuna on Appendix I of the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species (CITES). &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
An Appendix I listing would ban all international commercial trade in Atlantic bluefin tuna, giving this endangered species a chance to recover.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“The U.S. has a vested interest in this issue, as a fishing nation of Atlantic bluefin tuna – so if the U.S. can see the bigger picture and back the international trade ban proposal for the long-term survival of a species and a fishery, all countries can and should do so,” said Dr Sergi Tudela, WWF tuna expert. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

In addition, the U.S. is not asking for any conditions or delays of the ban unlike France and the European Commission.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“WWF now urges EU member countries to follow the US lead and drop any conditions in their own backing for the international trade ban, and calls on all CITES members to support the Appendix I proposal at the Doha Conference of the Parties. The time to save Atlantic bluefin tuna is now, and with a concerted global effort, we can do this,” said Dr Tudela.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The proposal to list Atlantic bluefin tuna on CITES Appendix I was submitted by the Principality of Monaco in October. The listing proposal is backed by countries including main Mediterranean fishing nations France and Italy as well as the European Commission and Parliament.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Atlantic bluefin tuna is at serious risk of commercial extinction because of decades of unsustainable and illegal fishing in the Mediterranean Sea, driven by demand from Japan’s luxury seafood markets. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
Latest official estimates suggest 36,282 tonnes of Atlantic bluefin tuna were caught in 2008, over four times the amount scientists say can be taken while allowing exhausted fish stocks to recover. It is believed the real catch figure may be well above this.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The 15th Conference of the Parties to the Convention on the International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES CoP 15) will take place March 13-25 in Doha, Qatar.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Convention is an international agreement between governments that aims to ensure that international trade in specimens of wild animals and plants does not threaten their survival in the wild.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2010-03-03</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>WWF welcomes Caribbean Spiny Lobster fishing ban</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=189983</link>

				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=189983&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/pablo_rico_wwf_langosta_cargada_de_huevos_1_317582.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;195&quot; alt=&quot;Spiny lobster (Panulirus argus) is the most important income source for a large number of coastal communities as it fetches high market prices. &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;Pablo Rico / WWF&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Central America, 1 March 2010 &lt;/strong&gt;– For the first time in Central America Caribbean, Spiny lobster fishing will be banned from the region’s waters during the species’ reproductive season, raising hopes for more responsible fishing practices in the region.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
Of all the fishing resources in this region, spiny lobster (Panulirus argus) is the most important income source for a large number of coastal communities, especially as it fetches high market prices.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The species is intensively fished from Belize to Panama and compared with other sea food products, it is considered a high valued dish. Both market demand and prices are ‘high end’, fuelling its overexploitation.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Lobster fishery has been the backbone of the fishing economy in Central America for over 100 years, but recently the dwindling catch has worried both the government and fishermen.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

“WWF celebrates this first regional closed season and is proud to have been part of this joint  effort’ said Bessy Aspra, WWF Fisheries Officer.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“This regional closed season is an important step for the protection of the most valuable fishing resource in the region, but it is also a clear sign of the regional and national commitment with the conservation of marine ecosystems.” &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The ban will be in place from the beginning of March until the end  of June.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
WWF works with governments, the private sector and fishermen in order to ensure the viability of lobster populations and to help implement better, more sustainable fishing practices. Scientific studies on ecosystem based fisheries management are also conducted, helping reach policy decisions such as the regional ban on lobster fisheries.  &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
This ban responds to the Fisheries and Aquaculture Integration Policy and the ordinance OSP-02-09 for the “Regional Regulation of Caribbean Lobster Fishing (Panulirus argus)”, issued by the Organization for Central American Fisheries and Aquaculture Sector (OSPESCA) and signed by the governments of the isthmus on May 21 2009.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2010-03-03</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>Release of rhino poachers exposes widespread enforcement failures</title>

				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=189943</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=189943&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/rhinocloseup_38629.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;93&quot; alt=&quot;A black rhinoceros (Diceros bicornis) in Zimbabwe. &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;WWF-Canon / Martin Harvey&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gland, Switzerland&lt;/strong&gt; - The release of six alleged rhino poachers from custody two weeks before a meeting of the largest wildlife trade convention is emblematic of the chronic lack of political will to enact enforcement efforts required to save this endangered species.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
A Zimbabwean court last week granted bail to six men arrested at Bubye Valley Conservancy, home to Zimbabwe’s largest remaining rhino population, in connection with rhino poaching. Charges included illegal possession of firearms and illegal possession of a rhino horn. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The incident, part of a surge in rhino poaching in Zimbabwe and South Africa, is made worse by a lack of enforcement support in Zimbabwe in particular.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
As 175 countries prepare to meet to for the 15th Conference of the Parties to the Convention on the International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES CoP 15) in Doha, on March 13, the increased poaching of rhinos and trade in rhino horns—compounded by failed enforcement efforts—is threatening to undermine conservation successes to date.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

Most rhinos are listed in the Convention’s Appendix I, which bans trade in their parts for commercial purposes.  Countries participating in the CITES convention have been tasked with combating illegal trade in rhino horn.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“Zimbabwe’s failure to live up to its obligations to CITES is unacceptable and has caused its already endangered rhino population to decline,” said Colman O’Criodain, Wildlife Trade Analyst, WWF International.  “The time has come for the CITES Parties collectively to decide how to address this failure.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This incident, coming so soon after Zimbabwe was specifically urged by the CITES Secretariat to tighten up its law enforcement to protect rhinos, will reduce Zimbabwe&apos;s ability to defend its wildlife management policies at the forthcoming CITES conference &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Last year, rhino poaching worldwide hit a 15-year high due to increased demand for rhino horn.  A recent report by TRAFFIC and IUCN, the International Union for the Conservation of Nature, showed that since 2006, 95 percent of the poaching in Africa has occurred in Zimbabwe and South Africa.  The report also showed that the conviction rate for rhino crimes in Zimbabwe is only three percent.  &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
WWF and TRAFFIC urge Zimbabwe, South Africa and all CITES Parties to uphold the commitments they have made as signatories to the Convention and dramatically improve law enforcement, including investigation of poaching incidents and prosecution of rhino crimes.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“Rhino poachers are currently operating in an environment where they are allowed to break the law without appropriate consequences,” said Steven Broad, Executive Director of TRAFFIC. “This kind of ineffective law enforcement increasingly undermines the success of more than a decade&apos;s work of bringing rhinoceros populations in southern Africa back up to healthy levels.” &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Most rhino horns leaving southern Africa are destined for medicinal markets in southeast and east Asia, especially Vietnam, where demand has escalated in recent years. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;</description>

				<dc:date>2010-03-02</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>New whaling compromise is step backwards for whales</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=189581</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=189581&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/iwc_minkewhale_27147_193079.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;49&quot; alt=&quot;While the compromise contains many positive elements for whale conservation that would help bring the IWC into the 21st Century, the compromise could legitimise ‘scientific’ whaling by Japan in the Southern Ocean Whale Sanctuary &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;WWF-Canon / Morten LINDHARD&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A new draft compromise on whaling released by the International Whaling Commission (IWC) today set a dangerous precedent that the international community must reject, WWF said.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
A working group within the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org/what_we_do/endangered_species/cetaceans/cetaceans/iwc/&quot;&gt;IWC&lt;/a&gt; today unveiled a new compromise aimed at unlocking the stalled negotiation process between countries fundamentally opposed to whaling and states that support it. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
While the compromise contains many positive elements for whale conservation that would help bring the IWC into the 21st Century, the compromise could legitimise &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org/what_we_do/endangered_species/cetaceans/threats/whaling/&quot;&gt;‘scientific’ whaling&lt;/a&gt; by Japan in the Southern Ocean Whale Sanctuary.  &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
“If there is one single place in the world where whales should be fully protected, it is the Southern Ocean,” said Wendy Elliott, Species Manager at WWF-International. “What we need is to eliminate all whaling in the Southern Ocean, including Japanese commercial whaling thinly disguised as ‘scientific research’.   But what we have now is a deal which could make it even easier for Japan to continue taking whales in this ecologically unique place.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The IWC has maintained a ban on all commercial whaling since 1986.  But, defying this ban, Japan, Norway and Iceland use loopholes in the IWC’s founding treaty to kill more than 1,500 whales a year. The loopholes allow whaling under ‘objection’ to management decisions (Norway and Iceland) and “scientific” whaling for research purposes (Japan).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The IWC also provides special protection to a critical whale feeding area, the Southern Ocean surrounding the continent of Antarctica, which the IWC established as a 50 million square kilometre whale sanctuary in 1994.  This extra layer of protection signifies the importance of this area as the primary feeding habitat of many of the Southern Hemisphere’s whale populations.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

Additionally, the proposal sets a process in motion that could endorse quotas which haven’t yet had a full and proper scientific review. “It is difficult to see how determining quotas through politics rather than science can be considered progress,” added Elliott.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The are some positive aspects of the compromise including increased efforts to secure the recovery of depleted whale populations, action on critical conservation threats facing whales such as such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org/what_we_do/endangered_species/cetaceans/threats/bycatch/&quot;&gt;bycatch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org/what_we_do/endangered_species/cetaceans/threats/climate_change/&quot;&gt;climate change&lt;/a&gt;, and improved governance and compliance.  However, the compromise cannot be accepted by WWF as long as it allows whaling in the Southern Ocean.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
The new compromise which will be discussed by a group of IWC countries at a meeting in March, is intended to be adopted by the IWC at its next full meeting in June this year.</description>
				<dc:date>2010-02-23</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>WWF: Cautious welcome to European Commission’s conditional support for bluefin tuna trade ban</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=189502</link>

				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=189502&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/tunafish_131840.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;94&quot; alt=&quot;WWF is concerned about the Commission’s proposal that entry into force of the ban be conditional on new analysis. &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;WWF-Canon / Ezequiel NAV&#xcd;O&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;WWF cautiously welcomes the EU Commission’s recommendation today that the 27 European Union member countries vote for a ban on international commercial trade in Atlantic bluefin tuna through a listing on Appendix I of the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES) at next month’s meeting in Doha, Qatar.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
But WWF is concerned about the Commission’s proposal that entry into force of the ban be conditional on new analysis, a procedure which is neither scientifically justified nor allowed under the CITES rules. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“Backing for the ban of international trade in Atlantic bluefin tuna is growing by the day and this latest announcement from the Commission confirms this”, said Dr Sergi Tudela, WWF’s tuna expert. “WWF is pleased to see this growing support but the conditional delay proposed the EU Commission is simply not allowed by CITES – and neither is it scientifically justifiable. The only real choice, if the fishery is to be saved, is to support full implementation of the ban as soon as possible to ensure the species has a chance to recover.” &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
After today’s recommendation in Brussels by the newly appointed European Commissioner for Fisheries, Maria Damanaki, and Environment Commissioner Janez Potočnik, the last remaining step to galvanise a formal EU bloc voting position in Doha will be at a European Council meeting between representatives of all 27 EU member state governments. This could happen as late as 15 March – after the opening of the CITES event – but is expected to closely reflect today’s recommendation from the Commission.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

WWF calls on European representatives to drop the conditional implementation proposal and urgently engage the support of the global community for the listing of Atlantic bluefin tuna on CITES Appendix I, which requires the backing of two thirds of the 175 CITES member countries present to be adopted.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“If the biggest Atlantic bluefin tuna fishing nation in the world, France, and the EU – whose fishing industry has the highest stakes in this fishery, holding more than 50 per cent of total catch quota – can decide to support a CITES Appendix I listing for the sake of preserving the fishery and the tuna, Europe should be able to convince the rest of the international community to follow. WWF calls on EU leadership to this end,” said Dr Tudela of WWF. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“WWF is highly concerned that the overwhelming acknowledgement of, and growing support for, the necessary ban could be undermined by any conditions which might delay or even derail the process. The best available data of barely four months ago already demonstrates as clear as day that stock levels are under 15 per cent of historical levels. The international trade ban must be voted in at CITES in Doha and implementation must begin immediately if we are to save tuna stocks. The time for action is now, and that action must be clear and unambiguous if the fish and the industry are to be saved,” said Tudela.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Others to have made public their support for Monaco’s proposal to list Atlantic bluefin tuna on Appendix I of CITES include the European Parliament and the secretariat of CITES itself. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
At the end of 2009 both the UN’s Food and Agriculture Organization expert panel and the scientific committee of the International Commission for the Conservation of Atlantic Tunas (ICCAT), the body in charge of managing the Atlantic bluefin tuna fishery, released analyses showing that the species amply fits requirements for an Appendix I listing.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“A CITES Appendix I listing for Atlantic bluefin will exclusively control international trade – so there will be no stepping on ICCAT’s toes. The international trade ban will rather help the fisheries management body to do its job by tackling the main obstacle to sustainable and science-based fisheries management – international trade on luxury seafood markets – while allowing artisanal and coastal fishermen to fish as usual and trade their tuna domestically. CITES Appendix I for Atlantic bluefin tuna is a win-win situation. With CITES and ICCAT working together there will be hope for Atlantic bluefin tuna and for its centuries-old fishing tradition,” said Tudela. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2010-02-22</dc:date>

			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>Year of the Tiger begins with big cats in big trouble</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=188502</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=188502&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/dsc00021_by_christopher_wong_1_1_314201.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;110&quot; alt=&quot;New camera trap photos of a tigress and one of her cubs obtained from a selectively logged-over forest in Malaysia show that tigers may be able to persist in such altered habitats. &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;WWF/Christopher Wong&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WWF outlined today the current top 10 trouble spots for tigers in a first-time interactive map that provides a unique overview of threats faced by wild tigers. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
The map comes as many Asian countries and the world prepare to celebrate the start of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org/tiger&quot;&gt;Year of the Tiger&lt;/a&gt;, which begins on Feb. 14. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
However, there are only an estimated 3,200 tigers left in the wild, and they face increasing threats including habitat loss, illegal trade and climate change, according to the map.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

There is hope though, as tiger range countries, conservation groups and organizations such as The World Bank will gather in Russia in September to lay out an ambitious agenda for saving wild tigers at a special summit.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“Tigers are being persecuted across their range – poisoned, trapped, snared, shot and squeezed out of their homes,” said Mike Baltzer, Leader of WWF’s Tiger Initiative. “But there is hope for them in this Year of the Tiger. There has never been such a committed, ambitious, high-level commitment from governments to double wild tiger numbers. They have set the bar high and we hope for the sake of both the tiger and people that they reach it. Tigers are a charismatic species and a flagship for Asia’s biological diversity, culture and economy.” &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In the lead up to the summit, all 13 tiger range countries recently committed to the goal of doubling tiger numbers in the wild by 2022 at a 1st Asian ministerial conference on tiger conservation in Hua Hin, Thailand. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The map is designed to raise awareness of these issues and help tiger range states achieve this crucial goal. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Additional threats to wild tigers highlighted in the map include:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Pulp, paper, palm oil and rubber companies are devastating the forests of Indonesia and Malaysia with critical tiger populations;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Hundreds of new or proposed dams and roads in the Mekong region will fragment tiger habitat;&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;Illegal trafficking in tiger bones, skins and meat feeds continued demand in East, Southeast Asia and elsewhere;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;More tigers are kept in captivity in the U.S. state of Texas than are left in the wild -- and there are few regulations to keep these tigers from ending up on the black market;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Poaching of tigers and their prey, along with a major increase in logging is taking a heavy toll on Amur, or Siberian, tigers;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Tigers and humans are increasingly coming into conflict in India as tiger habitats shrink;&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;Climate change could reduce tiger habitat in Bangladesh’s Sundarbans mangroves by 96 percent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Already, three tiger sub-species have gone extinct since the 1940s and a fourth one, the South China tiger, has not been seen in the wild in 25 years. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tigers live in 40 percent less habitat since the last Year of the Tiger in 1998, and they occupy just seven percent of their historic range. But they thrive in the wild when they have strong protection from poaching and habitat loss and enough prey to eat.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
“We know that wild tigers need protection, prey and secure habitat, but these alone will not save the big cats”, said Amanda Nickson, Director of the Species Programme at WWF International.  “What is also needed is sustained political will from the highest level of government in the tiger range states and this Year of the Tiger, and at the summit, these countries will have the chance to commit to making tiger conservation work.”    &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A glimpse of hope&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Although the map shows many trouble spots, there is still hope for wild tigers. New camera trap photos of a tigress and one of her cubs obtained from a selectively logged-over forest in Malaysia show that tigers may be able to persist in such altered habitats.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
The photo shows the tigress checking out a WWF camera trap with one of her two cubs. Researchers from WWF-Malaysia working in the area have caught the same female tiger on camera several times during the last several years, but this was the first time they saw that she had become a mother.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The photos, taken around September 2009, were from a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org/?uNewsID=185602&quot;&gt;camera trap&lt;/a&gt; retrieved last month, and set on a ridge of about 800 meters in elevation.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

“This is really encouraging to see a mother with her cub,” said Mark Rayan Darmaraj, senior field biologist, WWF Malaysia. “Such rare photographic evidence of breeding success magnifies the importance of this habitat for tiger conservation in Malaysia.”&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2010-02-10</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>International protection needed for coral used in jewelry – WWF, SeaWeb</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=188282</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=188282&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/redcoral1_cseaweb_dexph0250074_147419.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;110&quot; alt=&quot;Red and pink coral (also known as Corallium) are a type of deep-sea precious coral found in the Mediterranean and Pacific. &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;SeaWeb&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geneva, Switzerland -&lt;/strong&gt; Countries participating in a major endangered species trade conference in March must back better protections for red and pink coral, which are disappearing because of overfishing to make jewelry. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
Red and pink coral (also known as &lt;em&gt;Corallium&lt;/em&gt;) are a type of deep-sea precious coral found in the Mediterranean and Pacific.  Between 30 and 50 metric tonnes of these corals are fished annually to meet consumer demand for jewelry and decorative items. The United States alone imported 28 million pieces of red and pink coral between 2001 and 2008.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species (CITES) Secretariat today recommended that countries support increased trade protection for red and pink corals, based on the available population data for these species.  Science has shown that trade is having an adverse impact on red and pink corals’ ability to maintain healthy populations and to reproduce.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Meanwhile, the United States and the European Union are co-sponsoring a proposal to list red and pink coral under Appendix II of the Convention at the 15th Conference of Parties (CoP 15) in Doha, Qatar in March. Such a move would still allow trade, but only in legally and sustainably harvested coral and coral products.  &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
SeaWeb and WWF support the Secretariat’s recommendations and are urging CITES member countries to support the EU and US’s proposal.   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Kristian Teleki, SeaWeb’s vice president for science initiatives said, “Red and pink coral are among the world’s most valuable wildlife commodities. They are long-living, slow-growing species and have been intensively fished for centuries to meet demand in the jewelry and curio trade. A CITES Appendix II listing is needed to ensure these species aren’t fished to extinction.” &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“A CITES Appendix II listing would be in line with protection for other coral species,” said Colman O’Criodain, Wildlife Trade Analyst for the WWF Species Programme. “An Appendix II listing for red and pink coral would support local management measures and also help combat poaching, which regularly occurs in the Mediterranean.”    &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

Red and pink coral were proposed for protection at the last Conference of Parties in 2007. The parties initially voted in favor of the proposal, but the vote was overturned in a secret ballot on the final day of the conference, after intensive lobbying from industry interests.  Parties will once again take to the floor during CoP 15, March 13 to 25, to consider the proposal. Alongside red and pink coral, several species of sharks, and Atlantic bluefin tuna will also be considered for trade protection.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2010-02-05</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>WWF Turtle Workshop</title>

				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=188161</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=188161&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/img_0655_313421.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;219&quot; alt=&quot;Nakalou Turtle Workshop Vanua Levu, Fiji &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;Matthew Hensby&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 10pt&quot;&gt;Last week the WWF South Pacific Programme Office (SPPO)&amp;#160;staged a week long workshop for the people of Vanua Levu in Turtle conservation and monitoring.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 10pt&quot;&gt;The workshop saw people from all over Vanua Levu including Mali, Yaqaga, Yandua, Namuka, and Kia gather together in Nakalou village, Macuata to learn more about the endangered Sea Turtle.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 10pt&quot;&gt;The first day of the workshop discussed with its students the importance of turtles in the South Pacific, how to spot the difference between the seven different types of sea turtle – six of which can be found in Fijian waters.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 10pt&quot;&gt;During the second day the workshops focus moved to the areas of turtle conservation and monitoring and students presented to the group their ideas to help protect fragile sea turtles in Fiji.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 10pt&quot;&gt;Following a short classroom session in the techniques of turtle monitoring, such as measuring, determining a turtle’s gender and flipper tagging, the students took to the beach to put their newly learnt conservations skills into practice.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 10pt&quot;&gt;The workshop achieved the rare task of tagging two small Green Turtles and catching a large 1.3 meter long adult female that will later be satellite tagged in Nadi.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 10pt&quot;&gt;The success of the tagging exercise means&amp;#160;that&amp;#160;we&amp;#160;will be able to&amp;#160;better understand turtle&amp;#160;movements around Fiji, particularity with the satellite tag. We gather a wealth of information every time we perform the task and it helps scientists and conservationists all over the world better understand these mysterious creations and thus better understand how to protect them.”&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 10pt&quot;&gt;Everyone involved was very happy with the outcome of this turtle workshop, not only was attendance excellent and, by all accounts, everyone fully enjoyed themselves, but we managed to flipper tag two small Green Turtles and catch one large enough to satellite tag! Opportunities like these are quite rare.&lt;/div&gt;</description>

				<dc:date>2010-02-04</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>France calls for international tuna trade ban</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=188102</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=188102&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/tunafish_131840.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;94&quot; alt=&quot;France’s call for an international trade ban on endangered Atlantic bluefin tuna is a strong political commitment, but it falls well short of giving this endangered species the immediate protection it needs from overfishing. &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;WWF-Canon / Ezequiel NAV&#xcd;O&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;France’s call for an international trade ban on endangered &lt;a href=&quot;http://panda.org/tuna&quot;&gt;Atlantic bluefin tuna&lt;/a&gt; is a strong political commitment, but it falls well short of giving this endangered species the immediate protection it needs from overfishing.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
French Environment Minister Jean-Louis Borloo made official today that France supports the listing of Atlantic bluefin tuna on Appendix I of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org/what_we_do/how_we_work/policy/conventions/cites/&quot;&gt;Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES)&lt;/a&gt;, which will effectively ban all international commercial trade.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
However, France is asking for an 18-month delayed implementation of the ban pending new scientific analysis of tuna stocks. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

“WWF is pleased that the French leadership among Mediterranean states is calling for the international trade ban for Atlantic bluefin tuna and we urge the French government to drop the call for an 18-month delay in implementing the ban,” said Dr Sergi Tudela, WWF’s tuna expert. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“This decision was made despite a comprehensive report made last year on the historical depletion of tuna stocks, which revealed that current stock levels are under 15 percent of what they once were. &lt;br /&gt;
The mechanism suggested by France for triggering the ban is not allowed under the text of the CITES convention, besides being neither scientifically nor economically justifiable.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“Atlantic bluefin tuna is in a state of severe collapse after decades of overfishing and reproducing stocks are dwindling to an all-time low – and the driver of this situation is clearly international trade,” Tudela said. “To give the species a break, an immediate ban of international commercial trade at CITES – without condition or delay – is the only logical step for the global community to take. Anything less is woefully insufficient.”&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
WWF urges France to up its pressure on other countries to join it in supporting the trade ban. The support for a CITES Appendix I listing of Atlantic bluefin tuna by a major European fishing country may free up the deadlock across EU member states and the European Commission, whose fisheries and environment commissioners have been at loggerheads for weeks in a failure to agree on the formal EC position. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Italy already voiced its support for the Appendix I listing last week, along with suggesting a three-year suspension of industrial fishing.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“It now falls to EU Presidency holder Spain, other EU countries, the European Commission and all governments that are members of CITES to follow France’s lead and throw their support behind an Appendix I listing for Atlantic bluefin,” Tudela said. “The trade ban must however take immediate effect and be implemented without condition if it is to be of conservation and economic value.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

The proposed listing on CITES Appendix I was originally tabled by the Principality of Monaco.  Fisheries experts at the Food and Agriculture Organization of the UN and the scientific committee of the management commission for this fishery (ICCAT) have both confirmed that Atlantic bluefin tuna meets the criteria for listing on CITES Appendix I.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Any future modification of a CITES Appendix I listing can only be carried out by formal proposal and discussion at subsequent Conference of the Parties (CoP) meetings. Indeed, Monaco’s proposal is accompanied by a resolution facilitating a review of the listing at the next CoP, if scientifically justified.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A listing on CITES Appendix I will benefit traditional fisheries such as the tuna traps that have lined the Mediterranean Sea since Phoenician times. These fishers will continue catching and selling tuna in domestic markets, while the bloated international purse seine fleets – the majority of whose catch goes to Japan – will be paralyzed.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Under a CITES Appendix I listing, fishermen can only catch tuna within national waters and sell to domestic markets. But France is also pushing for the establishment of an exclusive economic zone (EEZ) around its Mediterranean coastline. This would allow traditional sustainable tuna fisheries to continue their activity and sell their bluefin tuna across the European market. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
“WWF supports the establishment of exclusive economic zones across the Mediterranean Sea to encourage sustainable artisanal fishing in the longer term. The monster industrial boats – pumped with public subsidies – have dominated catches in the last two decades, putting artisanal fleets in jeopardy and destroying tuna stocks. It is time to reverse this perverse and discriminatory situation, and a CITES Appendix I listing will do just that,” added Tudela.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The 175 member countries of the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES) &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org/what_we_do/how_we_work/policy/conventions/cites/cites_cops/15th_meeting/&quot;&gt;next meet on 13-25 March in Doha, Qatar&lt;/a&gt;, where Atlantic bluefin tuna will be the headline marine species.&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2010-02-03</dc:date>

			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>French Guiana set to tackle bycatch</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=187501</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=187501&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/t_ted_presentation_nalovic_312221.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;171&quot; alt=&quot;The Trash and Turtle Excluder Device, or TTED, will limit accidental capture of larger marine species.  &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;T. Nalovic/CRPMEM&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;A new law requiring French Guianese shrimp fishers to use special devices that reduce unwanted fish catch will help better protect marine turtles and other vulnerable marine species in the region.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
As of Jan. 1, the country’s fishing fleet under the new law now has to use a device called the Trash and Turtle Excluder Device, or TTED, to limit accidental capture of larger marine species. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Widespread use of this device, which took three years to develop, will greatly reduce bycatch among shrimp trawlers. In French Guiana, tropical shrimp fisheries represent a major source of undesired bycatch. Without a bycatch reduction device in place, shrimp represents only 10 to 30 percent of the total catch, meaning the rest is made up of other marine species.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Nearly half of the world’s recorded fish catch is unused, wasted or not accounted for, according to estimates in an April scientific paper co-authored by WWF. The paper, &lt;em&gt;Defining and Estimating Global Marine Fisheries Bycatch&lt;/em&gt;, estimated that each year at least 38 million tonnes of fish, constituting at least 40 percent of what is taken from oceans by fishing activities, is unmanaged or unused and should be considered bycatch.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
The TTED is an improvement of a previous device, the Turtle Excluder Device, that consists of a rigid grill inserted at a 45 degrees angle in the trawl with an opening toward the top or bottom. NOAA has documented in research&amp;#160;a 97 percent&amp;#160;reduction in marine turtle  captures through using the device, and additional TED studies conducted  internationally have shown a reduction in large marine organism bycatch of  as much as 91 percent.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
After three years of trials, a prototype combining the advantages of different systems was identified. This model, the TTED, offers numerous advantages, including a 25 to 40 percent reduction of fish bycatch. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In addition, the TTED reduces sorting time and risks of injury due to sharks and rays being caught. The new gear also improves the quality of shrimps, which are less likely to be crushed in the bottom of the trawl, and may also lead to a reduction in the amount of fuel consumed by the boats.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
WWF will be talking about this successful project at the upcoming Seafood Summit in Paris, France, running from Jan. 31to Feb. 2.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The TTED is the culmination of years of research. With funding provided by the European Union and the DIREN (Regional Environmental Authorities), WWF commissioned a study from IFREMER (French Research Institute for Exploitation of the Sea) to determine which selective gear was the most adapted to fishing conditions in French Guiana.  These initial trials, conducted under experimental conditions, were carried out on board a shrimp trawler.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Following this work, shrimp industry’s members expressed the need to continue these experiments and to become more involved in the project. In response, WWF and the CRPMEMG (French Guiana Regional Fishery and Ocean Farming Committee) began working in close collaboration in order to test and develop the best gear for the French Guiana fleet.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

With technical support from NOAA and IFREMER, the CRPMEMG carried out numerous at sea trials in close collaboration with French Guiana fleets. Specific parameters where tested such as the shape and spacing between the bars of the selective grid. These trials allowed the fleets and the crews onboard the shrimp trawlers to understand the advantages of a more selective fishing gear and the benefits of using it in French Guiana.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Based on the results and the captains’ recommendations, the CRPMEMG decided to make the use of this TTED system mandatory by January 2010, when the annual fishing licences are issued.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The TTED was developed by the CRPMEMG and fishermen with the assistance of NOAA, IFREMER, the French Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries, R&#xe9;gion Guyane, the European Fund for Fisheries (FEP) and the WWF.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;meta content=&quot;text/html; charset=utf-8&quot; http-equiv=&quot;Content-Type&quot; /&gt;

&lt;meta content=&quot;Word.Document&quot; name=&quot;ProgId&quot; /&gt;
&lt;meta content=&quot;Microsoft Word 10&quot; name=&quot;Generator&quot; /&gt;
&lt;meta content=&quot;Microsoft Word 10&quot; name=&quot;Originator&quot; /&gt;

&lt;link href=&quot;file:///C:%5CDOCUME%7E1%5CIMorrison%5CLocal%20Settings%5CTemp%5Cmsohtml1%5C01%5Cclip_filelist.xml&quot; rel=&quot;File-List&quot; /&gt;&lt;o:smarttagtype name=&quot;stockticker&quot; namespaceuri=&quot;urn:schemas-microsoft-com:office:smarttags&quot;&gt;&lt;/o:smarttagtype&gt;&lt;!--[if gte mso 9]&gt;&lt;xml&gt;
&lt;w:WordDocument&gt;

&lt;w:View&gt;Normal&lt;/w:View&gt;
&lt;w:Zoom&gt;0&lt;/w:Zoom&gt;
&lt;w:Compatibility&gt;
&lt;w:BreakWrappedTables /&gt;
&lt;w:SnapToGridInCell /&gt;
&lt;w:WrapTextWithPunct /&gt;
&lt;w:UseAsianBreakRules /&gt;

&lt;w:UseFELayout /&gt;
&lt;/w:Compatibility&gt;
&lt;w:BrowserLevel&gt;MicrosoftInternetExplorer4&lt;/w:BrowserLevel&gt;
&lt;/w:WordDocument&gt;
&lt;/xml&gt;&lt;![endif]--&gt;&lt;!--[if !mso]&gt;&lt;object
classid=&quot;clsid:38481807-CA0E-42D2-BF39-B33AF135CC4D&quot; id=ieooui&gt;&lt;/object&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
st1\:*{behavior:url(#ieooui) }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;![endif]--&gt;&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;
&lt;!--
 /* Font Definitions */
 @font-face
	{font-family:SimSun;
	panose-1:2 1 6 0 3 1 1 1 1 1;
	mso-font-alt:宋体;
	mso-font-charset:134;
	mso-generic-font-family:auto;
	mso-font-pitch:variable;
	mso-font-signature:3 135135232 16 0 262145 0;}
@font-face
	{font-family:&quot;\@SimSun&quot;;
	panose-1:2 1 6 0 3 1 1 1 1 1;
	mso-font-charset:134;
	mso-generic-font-family:auto;
	mso-font-pitch:variable;
	mso-font-signature:3 135135232 16 0 262145 0;}
 /* Style Definitions */
 p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal
	{mso-style-parent:&quot;&quot;;
	margin:0cm;
	margin-bottom:.0001pt;
	mso-pagination:widow-orphan;
	font-size:12.0pt;
	font-family:&quot;Times New Roman&quot;;
	mso-fareast-font-family:SimSun;}
span.apple-style-span
	{mso-style-name:apple-style-span;}
@page Section1
	{size:612.0pt 792.0pt;
	margin:72.0pt 90.0pt 72.0pt 90.0pt;
	mso-header-margin:36.0pt;
	mso-footer-margin:36.0pt;
	mso-paper-source:0;}
div.Section1
	{page:Section1;}
--&gt;
&lt;/style&gt;&lt;!--[if gte mso 10]&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
/* Style Definitions */
table.MsoNormalTable
{mso-style-name:&quot;Table Normal&quot;;
mso-tstyle-rowband-size:0;
mso-tstyle-colband-size:0;
mso-style-noshow:yes;
mso-style-parent:&quot;&quot;;
mso-padding-alt:0cm 5.4pt 0cm 5.4pt;
mso-para-margin:0cm;
mso-para-margin-bottom:.0001pt;
mso-pagination:widow-orphan;
font-size:10.0pt;
font-family:&quot;Times New Roman&quot;;
mso-fareast-font-family:&quot;Times New Roman&quot;;}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;![endif]--&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;&quot; class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;span lang=&quot;EN-GB&quot; style=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2010-01-31</dc:date>
			</item>

		
						
			<item>
				<title>Tiger Range Countries and partners make new conservation commitments in Thailand</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=187762</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=187762&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/tigersplaying_37153_296325.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;92&quot; alt=&quot;Bengalski tigrovi u vodi (Indija) &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;Martin Harvey/WWF Canong&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hua Hin, Thailand &lt;/strong&gt;– Governments from across Asia’s tiger range countries (TRCs) sent a powerful message that new efforts to save wild tigers from extinction would begin immediately and called for total protection of critical tiger habitats as the 1st Asia Ministerial Conference on Tiger Conservation concluded today at the resort of Hua Hin, Thailand. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
The Royal Government of Thailand hosted the meeting. Thailand’s Minister of Environment and Natural Resources Suwit Khunkitti pointed to commitments in the Hua Hin Declaration, and urged other TRCs to follow through with consolidated technical recommendations that resulted from an earlier meeting in Kathmandu on tiger conservation: “We shall reach up to the highest levels of our governments for support at the Year of the Tiger Heads of State Summit in Russia. Let us join together boldly to save the wild tiger.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Thailand made a number of new commitments at the conference:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
•	Expansion of its SMART wildlife area patrolling program in its Western Forest Complex (WEFCOM) at Huai Kha Khaeng-Thung Yai&lt;br /&gt;
•	Assistance to its neighbor countries to repatriate tigers when the population of tigers in WEFCOM and Kaeng Krachan/Kuiburi becomes large enough to act as a donor source&lt;br /&gt;

•	Announcement that it would make funding for the ASEAN Wildlife Enforcement Network a permanent item in its budget &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Seven ministers, along with senior delegations from 13 tiger range countries, gathered with top wildlife conservation experts and representatives from international organizations and donor institutions such as the World Bank, Global Tiger Initiative, WWF, Save the Tiger Fund, Wildlife Conservation Society, USAID, FREELAND, and TRAFFIC, to energize the wildlife conservation agenda, update national action plans, and announce specific proposals to reverse the continuing decline of tiger populations. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
President of the World Bank Group Robert B. Zoellick, who launched the Global Tiger Initiative (GTI) in June 2008 together with the Smithsonian Institution, Global Environment Facility, and other partners, delivered a video message to the ministers and delegations, promising support for the range countries’ efforts and to spearhead sustainable development in Asia: “The World Bank stands ready to support regional projects in the tiger range countries and to mobilize the donor community and develop innovative financial instruments to support tiger conservation funds.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Populations of wild tigers have declined to only 3,200 worldwide, according to latest estimates, from 100,000 a century ago. The GTI is one of the drivers of the World Bank’s commitment to new strategies that balance economic development with nature conservation, biodiversity and environmental protection.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
Another significant development in Thailand came from Prime Minister Vladmir Putin and the Government of the Russian Federation, who officially announced plans to host the Heads of State Summit in September. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Hua Hin Declaration reflected agreement among the TRCs to redouble efforts on the ground to halt the decline of tigers and assist in recovery of habitats. An international donor conference is also planned later this year to support the countries to bring increased resources for integrated game-changing policy to save the species from extinction.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Michael Baltzer, Leader of WWF’s Tiger Initiative, said: “We are delighted to see a ray of hope for the tiger as represented by the tiger range countries’ commitment to work together to double wild tiger numbers by 2022. We look forward to seeing their pledges turn into firm actions in Vladivostok.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

All 13 tiger range countries were represented in Hua Hin. They include Bangladesh, Bhutan, Cambodia, China, India, Indonesia, Lao PDR, Malaysia, Myanmar, Nepal, Russia, Thailand, and Vietnam.	 &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2010-01-29</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>Climate change could drown out Sundarbans tigers - study</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=186721</link>

				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=186721&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/bengaltiger2_311105.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;92&quot; alt=&quot;Tigers are among the world’s most threatened species, with only an estimated 3,200 remaining in the wild. &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;Martin Harvey / WWF-Canon&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One of the world’s largest tiger populations could disappear by the end of this century as rising sea levels caused by climate change destroy their habitat along the coast of Bangladesh in an area known as the Sundarbans, according to a new WWF-led study published in the journal &lt;em&gt;Climatic Change&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
Tigers are among the world’s most threatened species, with only an estimated 3,200 remaining in the wild. WWF officials said the threats facing these Royal Bengal tigers and other iconic species around the world highlight the need for urgent international action to reduce greenhouse gas emissions.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“If we don’t take steps to address the impacts of climate change on the Sundarbans, the only way its tigers will survive this century is with scuba gear,” said Colby Loucks, WWF-US deputy director of conservation science and the lead author of the study &lt;em&gt;Sea Level Rise and Tigers: Predicted Impacts to Bangladesh’s Sundarbans Mangroves&lt;/em&gt;.  “Tigers are a highly adaptable species, thriving from the snowy forests of Russia to the tropical forests of Indonesia. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“The projected sea level rise in the Sundarbans will likely outpace the tiger’s ability to adapt.”   &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
An expected sea level rise of 28 cm above 2000 levels may cause the remaining tiger habitat in the Sundarbans to decline by 96 percent, pushing the total population to fewer than 20 breeding tigers, according to the study.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Action on climate change needed to save the Sundarbans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Unless immediate action is taken, the Sundarbans, its wildlife and the natural resources that sustain millions of people may disappear within 50 to 90 years, the study states. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
“The mangrove forest of the Bengal tiger now joins the sea-ice of the polar bear as one of the habitats most immediately threatened as global temperatures rise during the course of this century,” said Keya Chatterjee, acting director of the WWF-US climate change program. “To avert an ecological catastrophe on a much larger scale, we must sharply reduce greenhouse gas emissions and prepare for the impacts of climate change we failed to avoid.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The world&apos;s largest mangrove forest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Sundarbans, a UNESCO World Heritage Site shared by India and Bangladesh at the mouth of the Ganges River, is the world’s largest single block of mangrove forest. Mangroves are found at the inter-tidal region between land and sea, and not only serve as breeding grounds for fish but help protect coastal regions from natural disasters such as cyclones, storm surges and wind damage. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
Providing the habitat for between 250 and 400 tigers, the Sundarbans is also home to more than 50 reptile species, 120 commercial fish species, 300 bird species and 45 mammal species. While their exact numbers are unclear, the tigers living in the Sundarbans of India and Bangladesh may represent as many as 10 percent of all the remaining wild tigers worldwide.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Using the rates of sea level rise projected by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) in its Fourth Assessment Report (2007), the study’s authors wrote that a 28 cm sea level rise may be realized around 2070, at which point tigers will be unlikely to survive in the Sundarbans. However, recent research suggests that the seas may rise even more swiftly than what was predicted in the 2007 IPCC assessment.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Tigers already threatened by poaching and habitat loss&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
In addition to climate change, the Sundarbans tigers, like other tiger populations around the world already face tremendous threats from poaching and habitat loss. Tiger ranges have decreased by 40 percent over the past decade, and tigers today occupy less than seven percent of their original range. Scientists fear that accelerating deforestation and rampant poaching could push some tiger populations to the same fate as their now-extinct Javan and Balinese relatives in other parts of Asia. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tigers are poached for their highly prized skins and body parts, which are used in traditional Chinese medicine. The 2010 Year of the Tiger will mark an important year for conservation efforts to save wild tigers, with WWF continuing to play a vital role in implementing bold new strategies to save this magnificent Asian big cat.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Recommendations in the study include:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Locally, governments and natural resource managers should take immediate steps to conserve and expand mangroves while preventing poaching and retaliatory killing of tigers.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Regionally, neighboring countries should increase sediment delivery and freshwater flows to the coastal region to support agriculture and replenishment of the land;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Globally, governments should take stronger action to limit greenhouse gas emissions;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;2010 is the &apos;Year of the Tiger&apos;, and a year for action to save this species&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“It’s disheartening to imagine that the Sundarbans – which means ‘beautiful forest’ in Bengali – could be gone this century, along with its tigers,” Loucks said. “We very much hope that in this, the Year of the Tiger, the world will focus on curtailing the immediate threats to these magnificent creatures and preparing for the long-term impacts of climate change.”</description>
				<dc:date>2010-01-20</dc:date>

			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>Seafood ecolabels under the spotlight in new WWF report</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=186062</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=186062&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/web_229724_309421.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;110&quot; alt=&quot;A beach-side fish shop selling fresh, sustainable, line caught cod, Aldeburgh, Suffolk, UK. &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;Paul Sunters / WWF - Canon&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gland, Switzerland &lt;/strong&gt;– The Marine Stewardship Council (MSC) comes out on top in a new report commissioned by WWF that reveals poor performance among other assessed seafood ecolabelling schemes and calls for improvements across the board to strengthen their effectiveness.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Accenture’s non-profit practice, Accenture Development Partnerships (ADP) compared and ranked seven fishery certification schemes that use ecolabels on seafood products against a set of WWF criteria that focus on the schemes’ effectiveness in addressing the health of fisheries and oceans. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The MSC is ranked the highest in the ADP report,&lt;em&gt; Assessment of On-Pack, Wild-Capture Seafood Sustainability Certification Programmes and Seafood Ecolabel&lt;/em&gt;s, with a score of just over 95 percent compliance to the assessment’s criteria requirements. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Many seafood ecolabels are inadequate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The report finds that except for the MSC, the other assessed schemes - Naturland, Friend of the Sea, Krav, AIDCP, Mel-Japan and Southern Rocklobster - do not evaluate fisheries across all criteria to the extent required to support sustainable fishing and healthy oceans. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;“The findings of this assessment reveal serious inadequacies in a number of ecolabels and cast doubt on their overall contribution to effective fisheries management and sustainability.” said Miguel Jorge, Director of WWF International’s Marine Programme.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;“While the assessment shows the MSC comes out best in class using the most rigorous programme out there, it is not perfect. Improvements are needed across the board to ensure all seafood ecolabels deliver on their promise.”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Assessment of ecolabels based on best practice guidelines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The criteria used in the assessment reflect best practices for fisheries ecolabelling certification schemes with the Food and Agriculture Organization’s (FAO) 2005 guidelines for ecolabelling forming the basis for the criteria. Standards developed by the International Social and Environmental Accreditation and Labelling Alliance (ISEAL) and elements from WWF’s framework for ecosystem-based management of marine fisheries were added. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The assessment points to significant differences in transparency, information availability, structure and accuracy of claims made by each scheme. Aside from the MSC, all other schemes assessed have substantial shortcomings in the area of transparency and information provision.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;“The growth of seafood ecolabels over the last ten years attests to the strong demand from consumers and seafood companies who want seafood from better fisheries.” added Jorge.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;“But with the proliferation of ecolabels and the variability of these schemes there is a real risk of confusion, or worse still a lack of confidence in seafood ecolabelling among buyers and consumers.”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Working with the seafood industry to protect life in the oceans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As part of WWF’s efforts to implement sustainable fishing practices globally to protect marine life and ocean habitats, the conservation organization works with major seafood buyers to use their purchasing power to secure seafood from sustainable sources and assess their current supply chain. The report is intended to address confusion expressed by this group and inform their choices.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The most credible ecolabelling schemes accepted in international fora are voluntary, third party, operated independently and involving interested parties.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seafood ecolabels should reflect on their contribution to marine conservation &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In addition to fisheries certification scheme efforts to address sustainable fishing, other issues including carbon footprint, animal welfare and social issues such as worker’s rights are growing in public consciousness. WWF calls on the seafood ecolabelling community to develop internationally agreed criteria for these priority issues and establish evaluation mechanisms.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;“We recommend the assessed schemes reflect on their contribution to marine conservation and use the report as a guide to how best to assess and evaluate fisheries seeking their ecolabel.” added Jorge&lt;br /&gt;. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; top: -21px; margin-left: -20px; margin-right: -20px;&quot; width=&quot;95%&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image-main&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;95%&quot; src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/original/fishing_ecolabels_ranked.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graph of ecolabels weighted average scoring performance. Marine Stewardship Council - 95.63%, Naturland - 64.56%, Friend of the Sea - 55.83%, Krav - 50.00%, AIDCP - 48.06%, MEL-Japan - 40.29%, Southern Rocklobster - 26.70%&quot; title=&quot;Ecolabels weighted average scoring performance.  Marine Stewardship Council: 95.63%, Naturland: 64.56%, Friend of the Sea: 55.83%, Krav: 50.00%, AIDCP: 48.06%, MEL&amp;dash;Japan: 40.29%, Southern Rocklobster: 26.70% - &#xa9; WWF&quot; class=&quot;cmstooltip&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div width=&quot;95%&quot; style=&quot;padding: 20px; position: relative; top: -45px; left: -20px; margin-right: -40px;&quot;&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/center&gt;</description>

				<dc:date>2010-01-18</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>Camera traps yield first-time film of tigress and cubs</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=185602</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=185602&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/tnl_00003782__c__des_syafrizal_307441.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;220&quot; alt=&quot;Karmila Parakkasi the coordinator of WWF-Indonesia&apos;s Tiger Research Team checking camera trap installed in Tesso Nilo National Park, Riau Province, Indonesia &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;WWF-Indonesia / Des Syafrizal&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jakarta, Indonesia &lt;/strong&gt;– Camera traps deep in the Sumatran jungle have captured first-time images of a rare female tiger and her cubs, giving researchers unique insight into the elusive tiger’s behaviour.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br&gt;
After a month in operation, specially designed video cameras installed by WWF-Indonesia’s researchers seeking to record tigers in the Sumatran jungle caught the mother tiger and her cubs on film as they stopped to sniff and check out the camera trap.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There are as few as 400 Sumatran tigers left in the wild and they are under relentless pressure from poaching and clearing of their habitat. After five years of studying tigers using wildlife-activated camera traps set up in the forest, these are the first images of a tiger with offspring. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“We are very concerned though, because the territory of this tigress and its cubs is being rapidly cleared by two global paper companies, palm oil plantations, encroachers, and illegal loggers. Will the cubs survive to adulthood in this environment?” said Karmila Parakkasi, the leader of WWF-Indonesia’s Sumatran tiger research team.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

The discovery comes as WWF prepares to launch a campaign on 14 Feb. 2010, to coincide with the start of the Year of the Tiger in the Chinese calendar. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The year-long, Tx2: Double or Nothing campaign aims to raise the bar for tiger conservation by securing high-level political commitment at a Heads of State Tiger Summit in September in Vladivostok, Russia to be hosted by Prime Minister Vladimir Putin, and supported by WWF and other partners of the Global Tiger Initiative, including the World Bank. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“We want to change the course of tiger conservation,” said Mike Baltzer, leader of WWF’s global Tiger Initiative. “It’s not just about saving the tiger from extinction, but about doubling their number by 2022.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
With wild tiger numbers as low as 3,200, and a systematic attempt underway to wipe them out of the forests in Asia, more must be done to ensure this charismatic species and flagship for Asia&apos;s biological diversity, culture and economy is not lost forever. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
In addition to the tigress and cubs’ footage, the video camera also captured images of a male Sumatran tiger and its prey, wild boar and deer, as well as many other species such as tapirs, macaques, porcupines and civets.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Infrared-triggered camera traps, which are activated upon sensing body heat in their path, have become an important tool to identify which areas of the forest are used by tigers, and to identify individual animals to monitor the population. WWF has operated dozens of cameras throughout the central Sumatran province of Riau.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Parakkasi and her team first captured still images of the tigress and its cub in July 2009 through still camera traps. The photos were, however, not very clear. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

“We were not so sure how many cubs there were,” she said. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Video camera traps were then installed in September at the same location to clarify the initial findings.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
WWF’s tiger research team set up four of the video camera traps in known tiger routes in a forested “wildlife corridor” that allows animals to move between two protected areas in central Sumatra – Rimbang Baling Wildlife Reserve in Riau and Bukit Tigapuluh National Park in both Riau and Jambi provinces. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“When these cubs are old enough to leave their mother, which will be soon, they will have to find their own territory,” said Ian Kosasih, WWF-Indonesia’s Forest Programme Director. “Where will they go? As tiger habitat shrunk with so much of the surrounding area having been cleared, the tigers will have a very hard time avoiding encounters with people. That will then be very dangerous for everyone involved.”&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
“With this clear scientific evidence of tiger presence, WWF calls for formal establishment of the area between Rimbang Baling and Bukit Tigapuluh forests as a protected wildlife corridor,” Kosasih said.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
WWF is also urging the paper companies operating in the area – Sinar Mas/APP and APRIL – as well as palm oil plantations to help protect all high conservation value forests under their control that are the habitat of tigers and other endangered species. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://panda.org/tiger&quot;&gt;Learn more about tigers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2010-01-07</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>Sustainability standards completed for tilapia farming</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=184801</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=184801&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/tilapia_farm_in_ecuador__by_aaron_272535.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;110&quot; alt=&quot;New global standards will allow the tilapia industry to grow while minimizing its impacts, such as non-native tilapia being introduced and chemicals being released into the water &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;Aaron McNevin / WWF US&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Washington D.C. -&lt;/strong&gt; Global standards addressing the negative impacts of tilapia farming on the environment and society have been finalized. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
They are the first set of final standards produced through the Aquaculture Dialogues, a series of roundtables coordinated by WWF.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The standards are the final product of the Tilapia Aquaculture Dialogue, a network of more than 200 people – including producers, conservationists and scientists – created in 2005 to help transform the aquaculture industry. Many of the participants are from the world’s leading tilapia producing regions, including Central America and Asia. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“With almost 75 percent of the world’s tilapia coming from a farm, instead of being raised in the wild, the need for credible standards is critical and timely,” said Dr. Aaron McNevin of WWF, tilapia Dialogue coordinator and Dialogue Steering Committee member.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

The standards will allow the tilapia industry to grow while minimizing its impacts, such as non-native tilapia being introduced and chemicals being released into the water. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“There are other tilapia standards on the market but these standards have staying power because they were developed by a broad and diverse group of experts through a very transparent process,” McNevin said. “The standards also will have a long shelf life because they are metrics-based, which is the only way to really know if the tilapia industry is reducing its environmental footprint.”  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The certification costs will be low compared to most certification programs because the standards focus on reducing a set number of key impacts instead of a long list of issues. The relatively low cost will make it easier for small- and large-scale producers to adopt the standards. Farmers who adopt the standards will be eligible for certification by early 2010.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Aquaculture Stewardship Council (ASC), a new entity that will be in operation in 2011, will be responsible for working with independent, third party entities to certify farms that are in compliance with all of the standards created through the Aquaculture Dialogues process, including the tilapia standards. In the meantime, this role will be filled by GLOBALGAP, a private sector body that sets voluntary standards. GLOBALGAP will certify tilapia producers by supplementing its existing food safety, environmental and social requirements with the new standards. GLOBALGAP Is expected to begin offering this new certification option to tilapia producers by the end of 2009.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
“We support the tilapia standards because they will help us tell our customers the story they want and deserve to hear – that they are eating tilapia which was raised in an environmentally friendly way,” said Craig Watson, Vice President of Agricultural Sustainability of Sysco Corporation, the largest foodservice distributer in the United States. “And with the ASC in place, we will have the assurance that the standards will be adhered to properly, which will bring credibility and longevity to the standards.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The tilapia standards are based on almost five years of discussions and research, as well as feedback received from more than 50 stakeholders when the draft standards were posted for review. The steering committee that managed the Dialogue process used all of this information to develop the final product. The committee included representatives from Regal Springs Trading Company, Sustainable Fisheries Partnership, New England Aquarium, Aquamar, Rain Forest Aquaculture and WWF.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“The end result of this process is a product our customers can be proud of because they know it is based on the best input from scientists, producers and NGOs,” said committee member Mike Picchietti of Regal Springs. “And the timing of it is perfect because the standards will allow the tilapia industry to grow without having a negative impact on the environment and society.” &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

The standards will be amended over time to incorporate new science and to encourage continuous improvement on the farm. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Through the Aquaculture Dialogues, standards for 12 aquaculture species will be created. The Dialogue process includes 2,000 people.The goal of the Dialogues is to follow the International Social and Environmental Accreditation and Labeling Alliance’s guidelines for creating environmental and social standards. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2009-12-18</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>

				<title>UN experts back proposal for bluefin tuna trade ban</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=184061</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=184061&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/bluefin_tuna_jumping_305660.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;61&quot; alt=&quot;A juvenile bluefin tuna jumping from the water in the Mediterranean Sea. UN experts now say evidence shows the endangered Atlantic bluefin tuna meets the requirements for an international trade ban. &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;WWF / F. Bassemayousse&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rome, Italy&lt;/strong&gt; - United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) experts say evidence shows the endangered Atlantic bluefin tuna meets the requirements for an international trade ban.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
The experts met as a panel last week to discuss trade regulations governing six commercially traded marine species and whether to recommend further action to protect them from overfishing. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Other species considered by the panel included spiny dogfish, porbeagle, red and pink corals, scalloped hammerhead sharks and oceanic white tip shark.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The FAO’s panel is highly influential in how countries vote during the Conference of the Parties to the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES), which will hold its 15th annual meeting in March in Doha, Qatar. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

Countries with strong fisheries interests often rely on advice from the panel on how to vote during those meetings, meaning that the long-term survival of some endangered species often depends on the FAO panel’s recommendations.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The FAO opened its statement today saying that &quot;a majority of the panel agreed that the available evidence supports the proposal listing under CITES Appendix I of Atlantic bluefin tuna (Thunnus thynnus)&quot; and later highlighted that &quot;an Appendix I listing would be likely to reduce the bluefin catches from both component populations. This would assist to ensure that recent unsustainable catches in the east Atlantic and Mediterranean are reduced.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
CITES, which is an international agreement between governments that works to ensure that international trade in wild species does not threaten their survival, normally offers its own scientific assessment on all the proposals it receives. However, in response to the concerns of larger fishing countries, it made an agreement with FAO that tasks the organization with conducting its own technical assessment of proposals for commercially traded marine species.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
This week’s recommendation from the FAO panel came after the scientific committee of the International Commission for the Conservation of Atlantic Tunas (ICCAT), the regional fisheries management organization in charge of the Atlantic bluefin fishery, had already shown through their own analysis that the species meets the criteria for a ban on international trade. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Today’s comments from the UN backing stronger protection measures are a crucial contribution to efforts to save the Atlantic bluefin tuna,” said Dr Sergi Tudela, Head of Fisheries at WWF Mediterranean. “A listing on Appendix I of CITES, which would temporarily ban all international commercial trade, is the best option by far to ensure the recovery and long-term survival of Atlantic bluefin tuna, now severely overfished.&quot; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;We all want the same thing ultimately - a sustainable, thriving fishery and trade of this species, but to achieve that goal some drastic measures are necessary now to give the fish a break.” &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

“WWF urges all CITES Contracting Parties to adopt a strong position on the Atlantic bluefin tuna listing proposal to ensure a positive vote for the temporary trade ban in Doha - and thus a chance to save this icon of the oceans.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In addition, the panel recommended stricter trade controls through listing on CITES Appendix II for porbeagle, scalloped hammerhead and oceanic white tip sharks. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
However, they also said that spiny dogfish or red and pink corals did not meet the criteria for stronger trade controls.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
WWF welcomed the panel’s recommendations on porbeagle, scalloped hammerhead and oceanic white tip sharks but expressed disappointment that these experts failed to see the importance of giving spiny dogfish and red and pink corals the same trade controls.  &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
The panel recognized that “inadequate management in many areas of distribution of these species represents a cause for ‘serious concern,’” and it recommended that national governments and regional fisheries management organizations remedy the situation on their own.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
WWF does not agree that this will be enough to save these species, and believes that these species need the support of a CITES Appendix II listing.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
WWF is concerned that in cases such as red coral the panel assumed that, where data are lacking on how much is harvested, that the species is not overharvested. This is contrary to the precautionary principle that lies at the heart of conservation decision-making. In fact, the reason the data are lacking is usually because the proper research has not been conducted or because countries are failing to report their catches. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

A detailed report on the recommendations of the panel will be released by the FAO next month.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2009-12-15</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>Flaws in protection measures hurt Bigeye tuna stocks</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=182921</link>

				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=182921&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/bigeye_trevally_bigeye_jack_caranxsexfasciatus_freund106377_280321.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;81&quot; alt=&quot;Failure by the Western Central Pacific Fisheries Commission (WCPFC) to manage fish stocks properly is contributing to the reduction of Bigeye tuna and other fish. &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;J&#xfc;rgen FREUND / WWF-Canon&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cambridge, UK &lt;/strong&gt;— Failure by the Western Central Pacific Fisheries Commission (WCPFC) to manage fish stocks properly is contributing to the reduction of Bigeye tuna and other fish. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
WWF and TRAFFIC, the wildlife trade monitoring network, said today that the regional fisheries management organization must address these flaws when they meet this week in Tahiti.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“TRAFFIC and WWF are particularly concerned that the efforts made by WCPFC to reduce fishing effort to try and protect Bigeye tuna stocks in the Pacific have failed according to the Commission’s Scientific Committee,” said Glenn Sant, TRAFFIC’s Global Marine Programme Leader. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“Tuna Commissions need to listen to the advice of their Scientific Committees. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

“It is of paramount importance that effective steps are taken to reduce the mortality of Bigeye Tuna immediately by 43 percent,” Sant said. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Global stocks of several tuna species are heavily overfished, with populations of Atlantic and Southern Bluefin tuna fished down to dangerously low levels. The Southern Bluefin tuna spawning stock is as low as 3 percent of its original size. More recently, concerns have been expressed over stocks of Yellow-fin tuna in the Indian Ocean.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“We live in desperate times as far as the health of our global tuna stocks are concerned,” said Sant. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In 2007, TRAFFIC and WWF published With An Eye to the Future: Addressing Failures in the Global Management of Bigeye Tuna, a report showing that Bigeye Tuna stocks around the world require better management. &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
“Last year, WCPFC tried to address overfishing of Bigeye Tuna in the Pacific, but their measures haven’t worked. Now there is no time to lose if Bigeye Tuna is not to join its cousins on the brink of fished-out over-exploitation.” &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Conservation of shark species caught during tuna fishing activities is another area of concern TRAFFIC and WWF have flagged for the meeting. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The organizations say a requirement that the landing of sharks should be mandatory, with fins naturally attached and all products tagged for traceability until their final destination. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

The sixth annual meeting of WCPFC is taking place in Tahiti, from Dec. 7-11. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2009-12-07</dc:date>
			</item>
		
						
			<item>
				<title>Europe pours tens of millions into bloating bluefin fleet</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=182741</link>

				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=182741&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/purse_seiner_206920.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;95&quot; alt=&quot;Europe&apos;s recent rhetoric has conceded a need to reduce the bloated bluefin fleet - but its actual practice has been to pour money into building newer and bigger boats like this Italian purse seiner. &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;ATRT&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brussels, Belgium: &lt;/strong&gt;Europe poured €34.5 million of EU taxpayers’ money into increasing and modernizing its oversize bluefin tuna fleets over the very period it was coming to concede that excess fishing capacity was a key factor in overfishing and illegal fishing of collapsing bluefin stocks.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
The information on 2000-2008 payments to the bluefin tuna fisheries was provided this week in response to a September question from Ra&#xfc;l Romeva i Rueda, a Spanish Member of the European Parliament (MEP) with the ‘Iniciativa per Catalunya Verds’, part of the European Greens.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The delayed response meant the information was not available for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org/wwf_news/news/?180682/Atlantic-bluefin-trade-ban-now-vital-as-tuna-commission-fails-to-take-action-again&quot;&gt;November’s meeting&lt;/a&gt; of the International Commission on Conservation of Atlantic Tunas (ICCAT), which witnessed several heated discussions on the reduction of fishing capacity &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
Rueda was told that the largest portion of the money - €23 million - was aid for the construction of new boats including modern purse seiners (industrial high-tech vessels with purse-like nets that scoop up large amounts of tuna).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Some €10.5 million went into the modernisation of existing vessels while, in stark contradiction to recent EU rhetoric about the need to reduce the size of the fleet, only €1 million went into decommissioning boats, all of which were smaller artisanal vessels.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&quot;I am shocked at the scale of subsidies &quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
The real level of subsidies is likely much higher, with unknown additional sums being pumped into the bloated fleet by EU member states.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Spanish boat owners were the largest beneficiaries of the 611 vessels involved, with the remainder shared between fleet owners in Cyprus, France, Greece, Italy and Malta.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Overcapacity has been identified as a key factor in catches that in 2007 were estimated at twice the legal levels set by ICCAT largely as a result of EU lobbying to be around twice the prudent levels advised by ICCAT’s scientists.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

Average catch size of Atlantic bluefin tunas fished in the Mediterranean Sea reduced by half during the period - for example in Spanish waters average catch size in 1994 was 159 kg, whereas by 2009 it was only 77 kg. These declines have been interpreted as indicating the dying out of reproducing tunas, and if such trends were to continue this could lead to the wiping out of the entire spawning population as soon as 2012.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“I am shocked at the scale of the subsidies given to the bluefin fleet,” said Rueda. “This shows clearly the hypocrisy of the EU, which insists on the need to conserve fish stocks while simultaneously encouraging the rapid expansion of a fleet that was already too large.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The European Commission’s response states that “the number of Community vessels licensed to fish for bluefin tuna in 2009 was 859 vessels or 52,553 Gross Tonnage (GT)”, a much larger capacity than the EU’s designated 2009 catch quota of 12,400 tonnes.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“It is a scandal that perverse EU subsidies have helped create a Frankenstein fleet continuing to aggressively target a collapsing species,” said Dr Sergi Tudela of WWF. “European citizens have given a gift of 34.5 millions Euros to the bluefin tuna industry which has resulted in the collapse of an ancient fishery, and what will happen next?&quot; &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
“WWF strongly demands that no more EU public money be pumped into this business.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Mismanagement of the bluefin fishery has fuelled moves to have international trade restrictions placed on Atlantic bluefin tuna at the forthcoming March meeting of parties to the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species (CITES) in Doha, Qatar.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2009-12-04</dc:date>
			</item>

		
						
			<item>
				<title>Species survival hinges on UN meeting</title>
				<link>http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=182661</link>
				<description>&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.panda.org?uNewsID=182661&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://assets.panda.org/img/tuna_at_market_131859.jpg&quot; width=&quot;146&quot; height=&quot;112&quot; alt=&quot;The fate of valuable marine species – including Atlantic bluefin tuna – likely will be decided at an upcoming United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) meeting. &amp;copy;&amp;nbsp;WWF&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;4&quot; vspace=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rome, Italy&lt;/strong&gt; – The fate of valuable marine species – including Atlantic bluefin tuna – likely will be decided at an upcoming United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) meeting next week.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
An FAO expert panel on commercially traded marine species is meeting Monday to consider whether it will recommend support for stricter trade regulations for the six species – a critical step to ensuring that they are not harvested to extinction.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In addition to Atlantic bluefin tuna, species under consideration include spiny dogfish, porbeagle, red and pink corals, scalloped hammerhead sharks, and the oceanic white tip shark.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The panel’s decision on each species will affect the outcome of the 15th Conference of the Parties to the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora, in March (CITES COP 15). Many countries that vote at CITES – especially those with strong fisheries interests - rely on the panel for advice on how they should vote.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

CITES, which is an international agreement between governments that works to ensure that international trade in wild species does not threaten their survival, normally offers its own scientific assessment on all the proposals it receives. However, in response to the concerns of larger fishing countries, it made an agreement with FAO that tasks the organization with conducting its own technical assessment of proposals for commercially traded marine species.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“This is a critical meeting as it could influence important decisions about the future of these species,” said Amanda Nickson, Director of the Species Programme at WWF International.  “Each one being discussed needs stronger trade restrictions as they are all overharvested, particularly Atlantic bluefin tuna.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“WWF calls on the panel to endorse these proposals and encourages CITES Parties to give these species the break they need for recovery.”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;</description>
				<dc:date>2009-12-04</dc:date>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>